a while back we covered the clinical
data indicating creatine's effects on
the brain but instead of repeating what
was mentioned there I'd like to dive
deeper into how creatina affects our
brain with the solid assumption that it
benefits our brain already in mind for
that we can lean on this study where the
researchers wanted to find out the
impact creatine supplementation had on
several brain cell measures like
mitochondrial function inflammation and
more this is an animal study because we
can't do this kind of research in humans
and since we already have human evidence
indicating creatine's benefits we can
lean on a study like this for more
details on the mechanisms so the
researchers gave animals uh creatine
supplemented diet or regular identical
diet without creatine then they
performed a series of brain function
measurements and instead of us bogging
this discussion with the uh mice had
brain improvements when we already know
that that happens in humans let's just
say that yes the creatine
supplementation improved performance but
why the researchers began by looking at
mitochondrial function one way to do
that is by looking at a seahorse assay
shown here what the researchers do is
isolate mitochondria from brain cells
and then measure the oxygen consumption
rate in these mitochondria oxygen
consumption is a metric of mitochondrial
activity we can see the amount of oxygen
consumed on the vertical axis then to
probe different sections of the
mitochondria they add different
stimulants and poisons to the
mitochondria to activate or inhibit
specific functions this tells the
researchers what aspects of the
mitochondrian are enhanced so for
example here ADP was added what does
that do if we look inside a
mitochondrian there's this complex of
proteins for Simplicity we'll reference
them by number complex protein 1 to five
complex protein 5 also known as the ATP
synthes interacts with ADP molecules
called adenosine diphosphate by their
full name and converts them to ATP
adenine triphosphate that's important
because your cells rely critically on
ATP molecules to fuel the majority of
the reactions inside your body ATP is
the major energy or currency of the cell
so if researchers saturate mitochondria
with ADP it's a precursor molecule what
might that tell us as researchers well
it tells us how well the mitochondrian
can convert ADP to usable ATP this is
called a coupled respiration essentially
we're measuring the capacity for
mitochondria to generate energy as we
can see by the light gray line which is
the creatine condition there's elevated
mitochondrial capacity for likely energy
generation through coupled respiration
we even see that further Quantified here
there's a a pretty substantial
Improvement in the creatine condition
however other measurements like maximal
respiration which identifies the highest
rate of mitochondrial activity are
unchanged with creatine so this tells us
that creatine improves the amount of
conversion of ATP to energized usable
cellular energy as ATP however exactly
how this happens is something that I'll
be getting into in the future because
it's an involved discussion on exactly
which compartments to the cell creatine
is found and it's an interaction of
energy molecules like ATP stay tuned for
that I'm already working on the video
anyway we know that creatine somehow
increases mitochondrial activity when
ADP is abundant which it often is when
there's a high energy demand like
exercise or even deep thought critical
thinking things that we're discussing
here as this relates to brain function
pretty neat right okay so I'll also be
covering more on mitochondrial
mechanisms as well as some inflammatory
mechanisms in the extended version of
this video which if you've been here for
a bit you already know where to find
that but in case I have not annoyed you
incessantly yet the extended version of
this video and access to all my work
including summaries exclusive videos
research reviews a podcast and more is
included with the physionic Insiders
Linked In the description well it
doesn't stop there because the
researchers also looked at some other
markers within the brain cells for
example a protein called
psd95 psd95 hasn't quite made itself a
household name so I'll introduce it to
you psd95 is a protein found in your
neurons brain cells that serves a key
function in your brain's ability to
undergo synaptic plasticity that's a
fancy way of saying changes to your
brain for your brain function to improve
as we see with creatine consumption
there has to be some level of change
that change can occur through a number
of mechanisms like having more receptors
on the brain cells uh that can bind to
communication signals release between
cells those are called neurotransmitters
so if more receptors is one way to
create change in the brain psd95 is a
protein that helps in that process more
specifically in anchoring receptor
you see let's say two brain cells want
to strengthen their connection to one
another one way as we discussed is to
increase the number of receptors on the
surface of the cell that allow the cells
to send neurotransmitters back and forth
and communicate signals these receptors
like ampa and nmda receptors are
stabilized by this
psd95 protein meaning they are anchored
in place psd95 will physically interact
with these key receptors and attach them
to the cell cytoskeleton essentially the
main structure of the cell called the
act in cytoskeleton in doing so these
receptors are stable on the cell
membrane and able to fulfill their
function beyond that psd95 also
interacts with signaling proteins and
allows them to scaffold so that they can
reach their target proteins for example
if a signaling protein needed to
interact with the receptor on the
surface of the cell and tag it to
increase or decrease its activity that
signaling protein could bind to psd95 to
interact with the receptor the point
being it significantly increases the
efficiency of cellular signaling so the
more efficient and adaptable the brain
cells are the better ons synaptic
plasticity and a greater ability to
learn and critically think okay so why
bring any of this stuff up now well
it's because creatine does nothing to
psd95 levels no quite the contrary the
left side you can ignore unless you know
how to read this style of data which is
why I included it for the rest focus on
the right side the creatine condition
the gray right bar clearly indicates an
over 50% increase so creatine
substantially increases psd95 levels in
the brain cells which would imply all
the benefit benefits that we discussed
before interestingly that actin
cytoskeleton protein that I briefly
mentioned before one of the proteines
that creates the structure of the cell
did not change this indicates that
creatin specific effect on affecting
certain components of the cell but not
others so we know that creatine affects
multiple mechanisms some I'll go over in
the extended version of this video from
mitochondrial effects to changes in the
cell receptor stabilization proteins in
the end because this is mechanistic work
we can't draw any applicable information
on it alone but this paired with
previous investigations on clinical data
indicates creatine is effective in
improving brain performance in fact I
cover the clinical data in humans along
with some key nuances right here I'll
see you over there
[Music]